Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
Leo Hurwitz collection,
1900-1900
89.5 cubic feet
George Eastman Museum
George Eastman Museum Moving Image Department 900 East Avenue Rochester, NY 14607 Phone: 585-271-3361 Fax: 585-256-3397 Email: stills@eastman.org URL: www.eastman.org
The Leo Hurwitz Collection consists of correspondence and papers (both business and personal), scripts, storyboards, publications and clippings, research materials, financial records, promotional material, interviews, festival materials, film and audio dating from 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991. The collection covers the whole of Hurwitz’s professional career and to a lesser extent his personal life, but with much overlap in the materials themselves. The collection documents Hurwitz's involvement with many notable figures, including Paul Strand, Elia Kazan, Joris Ivens, Paul Robeson, Ralph Steiner, W.E.B. Du Bois, Henri Langlois, Woody Guthrie, James Blue, and Edwin Rolfe.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to research upon request.
Acquisition Information
The collection was formally donated in 1999, with the memorandum of agreement signed by Manfred Kirchheimer on behalf of the Leo Hurwitz estate.
Custodial History
Materials were created, collected, and maintained by Mr. Hurwitz during his lifetime. Following his death, the materials were donated to George Eastman Museum by his estate. Materials arrived at the museum in multiple shipments between 1994 and 1998.
Funding for this finding aid was provided by a grant from the Council on Library and Information Resources’ Hidden Collections Program.
Biographical Note
The American filmmaker Leo Tolstoy Hurwitz was born on June 23, 1909, in the Williamsburg section of Brooklyn, New York. The youngest of eight, his siblings included his oldest brother William Hurwitz;Peter Hurwitz Hawley;Elizabeth Delza-Munson;Rosetta Hurwitz;Marie Hurwitz Briehl;Sophia Delza; and Eleanor Hurwitz Anderson. Hurwitz's father Solomon Gurewich (1860-1945), a tutor, arrived in the United States from Russia in 1898; his mother,Eva Riva Katcher, was a midwife whom Solomon met while teaching children in Eva's hometown of Rossava, Ukraine. Eva followed Solomon to the U.S. in 1900, bringing with her the first four of the couple's eight children; the rest would be born in the U.S. Solomon worked as a pushcart peddler and factory worker in Philadelphia and then New York City. Though anti-Bolshevik and a life-long anti-Communist Solomon nevertheless attended socialist, anarchist, and trade-unionist meetings, often accompanied by Eva; he also sent several of Leo's brothers and sisters to the Socialist Sunday School. [1] Leo Hurwitz attended Brooklyn's Dewey Junior High School and New Utretch High School, where he was the editor-in-chief of the literary magazine The Comet and president of the dramatic society. [2]
Hurwitz graduated high school in June 1926 and, having received a New York Harvard Club scholarship, entered Harvard College that September. While at Harvard Hurwitz majored in philosophy and psychology, with minors in fine arts and science. He also became a member of the Liberal Club. During his sophomore year Hurwitz decided against becoming a physician, and by his junior year he realized he wanted to work in film. In June 1930 Hurwitz graduated Harvard summa cum laude.
Returning to New York City Hurwitz began taking photographs for Harper's Bazaar and writing book reviews for several New York newspapers, including the New York Post. He also worked for an emergency relief agency at an orphanage across from the campus of the City College of New York. Hurwitz left the agency after several months and began working without pay as an assistant editor for Creative Art magazine, where the husband of his sister Sophia,A. Cook Glassgold, was the managing editor. Hurwitz's duties included securing copy and laying out pages of photographs by such photographers and avant-garde filmmakers as Ralph Steiner and Paul Strand, both of whom advised Hurwitz on his own photography. Steiner in particular taught Hurwitz the essentials of dark-room technique and photographic practice. Hurwitz also contributed film reviews to Creative Art, but due to a lack of funds and equipment his own filmmaking activities were limited to ideas for short films and a feature-length animated adaptation of Alice in Wonderland. [3]
In late 1931/early 1932 Hurwitz's interests in photography and film led him to the Film and Photo League of New York, where he was soon joined by Steiner, filmmaker/editor Sidney Meyers, and Lionel Berman. In December 1932 Hurwitz filmed the National Hunger March in Washington from its start in Boston --Samuel Brody,Robert Del Duca, and Steiner joined him in New York City -- and later edited the footage into Hunger 1932 (1933). [4] Additional Film and Photo League films on which Hurwitz worked as director, cinematographer, or editor include The Scottsboro Boys(1933) (in cooperation with the International Labor Defense) and Sweet Land of Liberty(1934) (with the Political Prisoners Committee of International Law).
In November 1933 the Film and Photo League inaugurated the Harry Alan Potamkin Film School at the Lexington Avenue headquarters of the Workers International Relief. [5] Named for the late film theorist and League member, the school was intended to meet the need for formal technical training and education in the history of film and film criticism. Hurwitz taught classes alongside other League members and soon advocated for the formation of a dedicated production unit within the League -- a properly trained "shock troop" consisting of "people who had a life interest in film" [6]. The idea met with resistance -- some members felt the idea of a select cadre of filmmakers was elitist and ran counter to the idea of the Film and Photo League as a mass democratic organization. [7] In response Hurwitz formed NYKino in 1935 with Steiner, Meyers,Jay Leyda,Irving Lerner, and Ben Maddow, many of whom comprised the core group of the Harry Alan Potamkin Film School. Initially funded by Hurwitz's salary from New Theatre magazine, where he began working as managing editor in 1934, NYKino shifted away from the League's strict adherence to documentary form, and began to incorporate dramatization and creative cinematography and editing into the depiction of real-life events. [8] NYKino's first projects included the completion of three films begun earlier by Ralph Steiner (Harbor Scenes,Quarry[a.k.a.Granite], and Pie in the Sky[1935]), all of which were edited by Hurwitz [9], as well as a dramatic March of Time-style newsreel "from a left-wing perspective" [10] titled The World Today, of which only two segments were produced (Sunnyside and The Black Legion). In 1935 Hurwitz, Steiner, and Paul Strand were hired by writer-turned-filmmaker Pare Lorentz to photograph the Resettlement Administration-sponsored film The Plow that Broke the Plains(1936) in Montana, Wyoming, and Texas. That summer, on July 2, 1935, Hurwitz also married the prominent dancer and choreographer Jane Dudley.
Upon their return from shooting The Plow that Broke the Plains, Hurwitz, Steiner, and Strand set about transforming NYKino -- at best a part-time endeavor for many of its members -- into what Hurwitz would later describe as "an independent production company with day-to-day continuity and with a full-time staff." [11]Frontier Films was officially launched in March 1937 with Strand as president and Hurwitz and Steiner vice-presidents. [12] (Steiner, along with Willard Van Dyke, would leave Frontier in early 1938 to form American Documentary Films.) Frontier Films' first completed production was Heart of Spain(1937), based primarily on footage of the Spanish Civil War previously shot by New Theatre editor Herbert Kline and edited by Strand and Hurwitz [13], followed by China Strikes Back(1937);People of the Cumberland and Return to Life(both 1938);History and Romance of Transportation(1939); and White Flood(1940). In 1937 production also began on a feature-length film about American civil liberties alternatively referred to as "Production #5," "Labor Spy," "Edge of the World," "Listen America!" and "Civil Liberties." [14] The film would take nearly four years to complete and would not be released until January 1942 by which time it had been renamed Native Land. The departure of additional members, a depletion of funds, and the U.S.'s entry into World War II all contributed to the end of Frontier Films, shortly after the theatrical release of Native Land in early 1942. [15]
Rejected by the U.S. Army on account of a functional heart murmur, [16] Hurwitz spent the early years of the war working on films for several government agencies, including the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs(Song of Freedom, 1942, and There Shall Be Freedom, ca. 1943); the United States Navy Bureau of Aeronautics(Tomorrow We Fly, 1943); the Office of War Information(OWI) ("Bridge of Men," 1943, and "On the Playing Fields of America," 1944); and the British Information Services, for whom Hurwitz adapted British documentaries for American use. [17] In general, however, work was increasingly difficult to find. According to Hurwitz the OWI had grown leery of him: An expedition to the Arctic to film a sequence for the agency's film "Bridge of Men" was canceled at the last minute due to an uncomfortable feeling that Hurwitz was a "premature anti-Fascist" [18] -- one early indication that his involvement with Leftist politics was becoming problematic.
In 1943, after Hurwitz and Strand's failed attempt to form a combat photographic unit for the Department of the Army, [19] Hurwitz drove to Los Angeles in hopes of joining Frank Capra's filmmaking unit of the U.S. Army Signal Corps. Hurwitz had agreed to the unit's use of footage from Native Land in Why We Fight: War Comes to America(1945), but his efforts to join the unit were rebuffed -- another instance, Hurwitz suspected, of "red-baiting." [20] The film industry, however, proved more welcoming. After being shown Native Land by Hurwitz's agent George Willner,David O. Selznick hired Hurwitz on a 13-week contract to write and direct a shipyard sequence for the home-front melodrama Since You Went Away(John Cromwell, 1944). [21] Hurwitz claimed to have shot over 40 minutes of footage, from which Selznick used only one shot. [22]
After nine months in Hollywood, Hurwitz made his way back east, stopping first in Detroit to write a film for the United Auto Workers[a history of the union possibly titled "The Story of Democracy -- The Growth of a Union"]. The film was never produced -- Hurwitz suspected internal political problems [23] -- and by 1944 Hurwitz was back in New York City. Through his friend Gilbert Seldes, then director of CBS Television, Hurwitz was hired as a network producer, director, and writer. Hurwitz remained at CBS for three years, during which time he became director in charge of News and Special Events. [24]
Shortly before the birth of his son,Thomas Hurwitz, in 1947, Leo Hurwitz left CBS to direct his second feature-length film,Strange Victory(1949), for producer Barney Rosset's newly founded company Target Films. Originally titled "Candle in the Wind,"Strange Victory dealt with the ongoing racial discrimination faced by returning African-American veterans in post-WWII America. The film won first prize at the 1949 Karlovy-Vary Film Festival, but was criticized in the U.S. for its "communist undertones," a critique which only strengthened many employers' reservations regarding Hurwitz and his politics. [25] These fears were formalized in 1950 when Hurwitz's name appeared in the infamous anti-Communist publication Red Channels: The Report of Communist Influence in Radio and Television along with 150 other members of the entertainment industry suspected of anti-American activities.
Hurwitz's unproduced projects of the period include feature-length adaptations of the novels Freedom Road by Howard Fast and Masters of the Dew by Jacques Roumain, and a film sponsored by Planned Parenthood. In 1949 Hurwitz proposed developing the "Movietel Camera," a motion-picture camera linked to a remote television monitor that would enable a director to see what the cameraman sees through the viewfinder. The camera was never produced.
Upon completion of Strange Victory Hurwitz attempted to return to CBS but found the network unwilling to rehire him for staff or freelance work, an attitude Hurwitz attributed to his blacklisting. [26] Instead, Hurwitz was hired as the Director of Television Production for the Souvaine Company, an independent production company headed by the composer and radio/TV producer Henry Souvaine. Hurwitz supervised the Souvaine Company's hour-long adaptation of Bizet's opera Carmen for the new CBS series Opera Television Theatre. (CBS seemed unaware of Hurwitz's involvement.)Carmen debuted on New Year's Day 1950, and though well-received, CBS's inability to secure a single sponsor meant Opera Television Theatre's next production,La Traviata, also supervised by Hurwitz, would be its last. [27]
In 1950 Hurwitz was hired by the United Nations Film Board to direct This Is the United Nations, a series of eight [though it appears the final number of issues was at least 15] theatrically released "screen magazines" highlighting the activities of the U.N. around the world. Hurwitz's work for the Souvaine Company continued. In 1951 he re-edited and supervised the musical re-voicing and printing of Lou Bunin's English-language adaptation of Alice in Wonderland(1951), a combination of live action and stop-motion animation originally released in France in 1949.
In 1951 NBC hired the Souvaine Company to produce America Applauds: An Evening for Richard Rodgers, a 34-minute musical tribute to the popular composer sponsored by the United Shoe Company. While the broadcast was a critical success for the network -- among its many featured performers was a young Mary Martin in her first television appearance -- any future work with NBC was not forthcoming. Their reluctance, Hurwitz believed, was due once again to his blacklisting. [28] That year Hurwitz also served as a script and production consultant for Prockter Productions' television adaptation of the radio series The Big Story. The episode was to serve as an "audition film," i.e. a pilot, for potential sponsor Pall Mall cigarettes and its parent company American Tobacco. Toward the end of 1951 Hurwitz was hired by Peter Lawrence Productions to adapt a stage production of J.M. Barrie's Peter Pan for a Christmas Day broadcast on CBS-TV. Though Lawrence enjoyed success with a 1950 Broadway production of the play starring Jean Arthur and Boris Karloff, the broadcast was canceled when a sponsor failed to materialize.
In 1952 producer Ben Gradus approached Hurwitz with a failed script written for the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York and asked Hurwitz to rewrite and direct the film. The result,On this Day(1952), "dealt fundamentally with the anxiety that everybody feels... about the cost of medicine when you're not insured," and called for health insurance and socialized medicine. [29] While working on the film Hurwitz was approached by Life magazine photographer Fons Iannelli with motion-picture footage he had shot with his own 16mm camera and tape recorder which allowed for portable, synchronized sound recording. Iannelli shot the footage inside the emergency room of an urban hospital and asked Hurwitz to edit it into a coherent promotional film that could be used to interest potential investors and producers. [30] The film,Emergency Ward(1952), clearly anticipated the Direct and Observational Cinema movements of the late 1950s and early 1960s, and captured the interest of Robert Saudek, the producer of the CBS-TV's Omnibus program. Saudek initially agreed to make at least one film with Iannelli's invention. Unbeknownst to Saudek, the blacklisted Hurwitz would write, direct, and edit the film, a documentary about a young boxer in training who must also support a wife and baby.The Young Fighter aired on CBS in 1953 and is now considered the first broadcast example of Direct Cinema. [31] Continuing to use Iannelli as a "front," Hurwitz began production on a second Omnibus film about the Lexington School for the Deaf titled Deaf Boy, but left the project after a falling out with Iannelli (Hurwitz claimed Iannelli attempted to hijack the series by deliberately exposing him to Saudek). A follow-up film, possibly about the Dust Bowl, was canceled. [32]
In 1953 Hurwitz was invited to New Mexico to serve as a consulting director on Salt of the Earth, a dramatization of the 1951 workers' strike against the Empire Zinc Company that was written, directed, and produced by fellow victims of the blacklist. Hurwitz, however, soon grew frustrated with the quality of director Herbert J. Biberman's footage and general disregard for Hurwitz’s advice. [33] Hurwitz returned to New York City before the film was completed, but eventually returned to assist with the editing in a secret cutting room in Topanga Canyon, California. Further disagreements led to Hurwitz once again exiting the production, leaving most of the editing to be done by Ed Spiegel and Hurwitz's assistant,Joan Laird. [34]
When support failed to materialize for Hurwitz's planned film adaptation of The Lonesome Train,Millard Lampell and Earl Robinson's folk oratorio about Abraham Lincoln, Hurwitz took over the directing and editing of Freedom of the American Road(1955), a film sponsored by the Ford Motor Company and produced by MPO Productions. Hurwitz also served as a consultant on a film for the New Jersey Railroad Association[title unknown] and The Earth Is Born(1956), the first in a projected series of short films based on the Life magazine science series The World We Live In.
In 1956 Hurwitz received funding from Film Polski to make The Museum and the Fury, one of the earliest films to deal with the horrors of the Nazi holocaust. Granted access to the Film Polski archives, Hurwitz was expected to make a film addressing the general effects of World War II on Poland. Hurwitz, however, focused instead on the destruction of Polish Jewry and Poland’s concentration camps-turned-museums. Finding the finished film too poetic, Film Polski refused to distribute it but allowed Hurwitz to purchase the rights for $5000. [35]
In 1955 Hurwitz was once again called upon to rescue a troubled film project, this time a U.S. travelogue sponsored by Pan American Airways and produced by Henry Strauss.U.S.A. was Pan Am's first film intended to lure foreign travelers to the U.S., but the project had become stalled for nearly a year and a half. Under Hurwitz's direction the finished film incorporated travel information with subtle satire, and introduced the formal technique of moving the camera across drawings and still photographs that would later become associated with the documentary style of Ken Burns. [34]U.S.A. went on to win several international awards and the prestige delighted Strauss and Pan Am, who wanted Hurwitz to direct several films in Japan. But U.S.A. would be the only film Hurwitz would direct for Pan Am: His political leanings and subsequent blacklisting rendered him ineligible for a U.S. passport (although he would go on to write Pan Am's 1958 short Voici la France). [36]
Dropped by Henry Strauss Productions, Hurwitz soon found work with Dynamic Films, for which he wrote two sponsored films:Pattern of a Profession(1959), which Dynamic Films produced for the American Dental Association, and Gift of Years(1960) for the National Committee on Aging. The first in a planned series titled Preparation for Retirement,Gift of Years was completed without Hurwitz's involvement: Having written a script, he left the project when rewrites were requested. [37]
In late 1961 Hurwitz returned to television after contacting Milton Fruchtman, the chief producer at Capital Cities Broadcasting, a small network of state capital-area television stations partially owned by Lowell Thomas. Fruchtman had secured the exclusive rights to videotape the trial of the captured SS officer Adolf Eichmann in Jerusalem, but he faced a personnel problem: the agreement stipulated the use of Israeli cameramen in the courtroom, all of whom would have to be trained in the use of television cameras since Israel at the time had no television industry. Hurwitz, whose activities at CBS often included training television cameramen (and who by now had been permitted a U.S. passport), arranged for Fruchtman to see his Holocaust-themed film The Museum and the Fury. [38] Impressed, Fruchtman hired Hurwitz to film what would become a historic, nine-month exposé of Nazi bureaucracy and the horrors of the concentration camps. As Capital Cities was the sole provider of videotape of the proceedings, Hurwitz's footage of the trial would be sold to television news outlets and broadcast throughout the world (with no television, Israelis listened to the audio portions on the radio). Afterwards Hurwitz edited trial highlights into Verdict for Tomorrow(1961), a 30-minute summation which was then distributed free of charge to television broadcast stations. [39]
Back in the U.S, Hurwitz revisited a film he had all but completed before leaving for Jerusalem:Here at the Waters' Edge(1961), a visual poem about the sights and sounds of New York Harbor co-directed by the photographer Charles Platt. Hurwitz now felt the film needed to be more concise, and edited out some 15 minutes of footage as well as the haiku he had composed for the voice-over soundtrack. In addition to the film, Hurwitz released an edited version of the soundtrack on Folkways Records titled Here at the Waters' Edge 1: A Voyage in Sound(1962). Hurwitz recorded material for a second soundtrack album -- selections from the writings of Walt Whitman,Hart Crane,Herman Melville,Alan Dugan, and Thomas McGrath, read by Melvyn Douglas over ambient harbor sounds -- but it was never released. [40]
Though still blacklisted from the television networks, Hurwitz was able to find work at National Educational Television(NET), once again through his friend Gilbert Seldes, who had by then left CBS and was working for the public television network. Seldes advised Hurwitz to stay away from political and public affairs and concentrate on cultural affairs programming. [41] One of the first projects Hurwitz was asked to write, direct, and edit for NET was Essay on Death: A Memorial to John F. Kennedy(1964) commemorating the first anniversary of Kennedy's assassination. The film was co-written by NET producer Brice Howard and co-edited by Peggy Lawson, a long-time assistant with whom Hurwitz had begun a relationship after separating from Jane Dudley in 1962. [42]
While never hired to the NET staff, Hurwitz went on to write, direct, and produce the acclaimed documentaries The Sun and Richard Lippold and In Search of Hart Crane(both 1966) for the network, all the while attempting to raise funding for such independent projects as a feature-length adaptation of Nathaniel Hawthorne's novel The Scarlet Letter.
In 1965 Hurwitz directed and produced Haiku, a 30-minute dance film featuring Jane Dudley's choreography. The same year a decision was reached in Hurwitz v. Directors Guild of America Incorporated, a lawsuit Hurwitz and five other plaintiffs brought against the Directors Guild of America(DGA) regarding the non-Communist loyalty oath required by the union for membership. The plaintiffs, originally members of the Screen Directors International Guild(SDIG) which had no such requirement, refused to sign the oath when the SDIG merged with the DGA in 1965. The DGA in turn refused them admittance into the union. In July 1965 the U.S. Court of Appeals decided the oath was "vague" and forbade the expulsion of anyone who refused to sign it. [43]